<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc editing="no"?>
<?rfc-ext parse-xml-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<rfc obsoletes="2732, 2396, 1808" updates="1738" category="std"
     ipr="full2026" docName="draft-fielding-uri-rfc2396bis-00">

<front>
  <title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>

  <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
    <organization abbrev="MIT/LCS">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>MIT/LCS, Room NE43-356</street>
        <street>200 Technology Square</street>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <region>MA</region>
        <code>02139</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
      <facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
      <email>timbl@w3.org</email>
      <uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials='R.T.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
    <organization abbrev="Day Software">Day Software</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>2 Corporate Plaza, Suite 150</street>
        <city>Newport Beach</city>
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>92660</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1-949-644-2557</phone>
      <facsimile>+1-949-644-5064</facsimile>
      <email>roy.fielding@day.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.apache.org/~fielding/</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
    <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>345 Park Ave</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>95110</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
      <email>LMM@acm.org</email>
      <uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date month='July' year='2002'></date>

  <area>Applications</area>
  <keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
  <keyword>URI</keyword>
  <keyword>URL</keyword>
  <keyword>URN</keyword>
  <keyword>WWW</keyword>

  <abstract>
<t>
   A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact string of characters
   for identifying an abstract or physical resource.  This document
   defines the generic syntax of URI, including both absolute and
   relative forms, and guidelines for their use.
</t>
<t>
   This document defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URI,
   such that an implementation can parse the common components of a URI
   reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
   possible identifier type.  This document does not define a generative
   grammar for URI; that task will be performed by the individual
   specifications of each URI scheme.
</t></abstract>
<note title='IESG Note'>
<t>
   This paper describes a "superset" of operations that can be applied
   to URI.  It consists of both a grammar and a description of basic
   functionality for URI.  To understand what is a valid URI, both the
   grammar and the associated description have to be studied.  Some of
   the functionality described is not applicable to all URI schemes, and
   some operations are only possible when certain media types are
   retrieved using the URI, regardless of the scheme used.
</t></note></front>
<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<t>
   Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI) provide a simple and extensible
   means for identifying a resource.  This specification of URI syntax
   and semantics is derived from concepts introduced by the World Wide
   Web global information initiative, whose use of such objects dates
   from 1990 and is described in "Universal Resource Identifiers in WWW"
   <xref target="RFC1630"/>.  The specification of URI is designed to meet the
   recommendations laid out in "Functional Recommendations for Internet
   Resource Locators" <xref target="RFC1736"/> and "Functional Requirements for Uniform
   Resource Names" <xref target="RFC1737"/>.
</t>
<t>
   This document updates and merges "Uniform Resource Locators"
   <xref target="RFC1738"/> and "Relative Uniform Resource Locators" <xref target="RFC1808"/> in order
   to define a single, generic syntax for all URI.  It excludes those
   portions of RFC 1738 that defined the specific syntax of individual
   URL schemes; those portions will be updated as separate documents, as
   will the process for registration of new URI schemes.  This document
   does not discuss the issues and recommendation for dealing with
   characters outside of the US-ASCII character set <xref target="ASCII"/>; those
   recommendations are discussed in a separate document.
</t>
<t>
   All significant changes from the prior RFCs are noted in Appendix G.
</t>

<section title="Overview of URI">
<t>
   URI are characterized by the following definitions:
</t>
<t>Uniform
  <list>
    <t>
         Uniformity provides several benefits: it allows different types
         of resource identifiers to be used in the same context, even
         when the mechanisms used to access those resources may differ;
         it allows uniform semantic interpretation of common syntactic
         conventions across different types of resource identifiers; it
         allows introduction of new types of resource identifiers
         without interfering with the way that existing identifiers are
         used; and, it allows the identifiers to be reused in many
         different contexts, thus permitting new applications or
         protocols to leverage a pre-existing, large, and widely-used
         set of resource identifiers.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>Resource
  <list>
    <t>
         A resource can be anything that has identity.  Familiar
         examples include an electronic document, an image, a service
         (e.g., "today's weather report for Los Angeles"), and a
         collection of other resources.  Not all resources are network
         "retrievable"; e.g., human beings, corporations, and bound
         books in a library can also be considered resources.
        </t>
        <t>
         The resource is the conceptual mapping to an entity or set of
         entities, not necessarily the entity which corresponds to that
         mapping at any particular instance in time.  Thus, a resource
         can remain constant even when its content---the entities to
         which it currently corresponds---changes over time, provided
         that the conceptual mapping is not changed in the process.
        </t>
  </list>
</t>        
<t>Identifier
  <list>
    <t>
         An identifier is an object that can act as a reference to
         something that has identity.  In the case of URI, the object is
         a sequence of characters with a restricted syntax.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
   Having identified a resource, a system may perform a variety of
   operations on the resource, as might be characterized by such words
   as `access', `update', `replace', or `find attributes'.
</t>
</section>

<section title="URI, URL, and URN">
<t>
   A URI can be further classified as a locator, a name, or both.  The
   term "Uniform Resource Locator" (URL) refers to the subset of URI
   that identify resources via a representation of their primary access
   mechanism (e.g., their network "location"), rather than identifying
   the resource by name or by some other attribute(s) of that resource.
   The term "Uniform Resource Name" (URN) refers to the subset of URI
   that are required to remain globally unique and persistent even when
   the resource ceases to exist or becomes unavailable.
</t>
<t>
   The URI scheme (Section 3.1) defines the namespace of the URI, and
   thus may further restrict the syntax and semantics of identifiers
   using that scheme.  This specification defines those elements of the
   URI syntax that are either required of all URI schemes or are common
   to many URI schemes.  It thus defines the syntax and semantics that
   are needed to implement a scheme-independent parsing mechanism for
   URI references, such that the scheme-dependent handling of a URI can
   be postponed until the scheme-dependent semantics are needed.  We use
   the term URL below when describing syntax or semantics that only
   apply to locators.
</t>
<t>
   Although many URL schemes are named after protocols, this does not
   imply that the only way to access the URL's resource is via the named
   protocol.  Gateways, proxies, caches, and name resolution services
   might be used to access some resources, independent of the protocol
   of their origin, and the resolution of some URL may require the use
   of more than one protocol (e.g., both DNS and HTTP are typically used
   to access an "http" URL's resource when it can't be found in a local
   cache).
</t>
<t>
   A URN differs from a URL in that it's primary purpose is persistent
   labeling of a resource with an identifier.  That identifier is drawn
   from one of a set of defined namespaces, each of which has its own
   set name structure and assignment procedures.  The "urn" scheme has
   been reserved to establish the requirements for a standardized URN
   namespace, as defined in "URN Syntax" <xref target="RFC2141"/> and its related
   specifications.
</t>
<t>
   Most of the examples in this specification demonstrate URL, since
   they allow the most varied use of the syntax and often have a
   hierarchical namespace.  A parser of the URI syntax is capable of
   parsing both URL and URN references as a generic URI; once the scheme
   is determined, the scheme-specific parsing can be performed on the
   generic URI components.  In other words, the URI syntax is a superset
   of the syntax of all URI schemes.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Example URI">
<t>
   The following examples illustrate URI that are in common use.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
ftp://ftp.is.co.za/rfc/rfc1808.txt
</artwork><postamble>
      -- ftp scheme for File Transfer Protocol services
</postamble></figure>
<figure><artwork>
gopher://spinaltap.micro.umn.edu/00/Weather/California/Los%20Angeles
</artwork><postamble>
      -- gopher scheme for Gopher and Gopher+ Protocol services
</postamble></figure>
<figure><artwork>
http://www.math.uio.no/faq/compression-faq/part1.html
</artwork><postamble>
      -- http scheme for Hypertext Transfer Protocol services
</postamble></figure>
<figure><artwork>
mailto:mduerst@ifi.unizh.ch
</artwork><postamble>
      -- mailto scheme for electronic mail addresses
</postamble></figure>
<figure><artwork>
news:comp.infosystems.www.servers.unix
</artwork><postamble>
      -- news scheme for USENET news groups and articles
</postamble></figure>
<figure><artwork>
telnet://melvyl.ucop.edu/
</artwork><postamble>
      -- telnet scheme for interactive services via the TELNET Protocol
</postamble></figure>
</section>

<section title="Hierarchical URI and Relative Forms">
<t>
   An absolute identifier refers to a resource independent of the
   context in which the identifier is used.  In contrast, a relative
   identifier refers to a resource by describing the difference within a
   hierarchical namespace between the current context and an absolute
   identifier of the resource.
</t>
<t>
   Some URI schemes support a hierarchical naming system, where the
   hierarchy of the name is denoted by a "/" delimiter separating the
   components in the scheme. This document defines a scheme-independent
   `relative' form of URI reference that can be used in conjunction with
   a `base' URI (of a hierarchical scheme) to produce another URI. The
   syntax of hierarchical URI is described in Section 3; the relative
   URI calculation is described in Section 5.
</t>
</section>

<section title="URI Transcribability">
<t>
   The URI syntax was designed with global transcribability as one of
   its main concerns. A URI is a sequence of characters from a very
   limited set, i.e. the letters of the basic Latin alphabet, digits,
   and a few special characters.  A URI may be represented in a variety
   of ways: e.g., ink on paper, pixels on a screen, or a sequence of
   octets in a coded character set.  The interpretation of a URI depends
   only on the characters used and not how those characters are
   represented in a network protocol.
</t>
<t>
   The goal of transcribability can be described by a simple scenario.
   Imagine two colleagues, Sam and Kim, sitting in a pub at an
   international conference and exchanging research ideas.  Sam asks Kim
   for a location to get more information, so Kim writes the URI for the
   research site on a napkin.  Upon returning home, Sam takes out the
   napkin and types the URI into a computer, which then retrieves the
   information to which Kim referred.
</t>
<t>
   There are several design concerns revealed by the scenario:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>
         A URI is a sequence of characters, which is not always
         represented as a sequence of octets.
    </t>
    <t>
         A URI may be transcribed from a non-network source, and thus
         should consist of characters that are most likely to be able to
         be typed into a computer, within the constraints imposed by
         keyboards (and related input devices) across languages and
         locales.
    </t>
    <t>
         A URI often needs to be remembered by people, and it is easier
         for people to remember a URI when it consists of meaningful
         components.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
   These design concerns are not always in alignment.  For example, it
   is often the case that the most meaningful name for a URI component
   would require characters that cannot be typed into some systems.  The
   ability to transcribe the resource identifier from one medium to
   another was considered more important than having its URI consist of
   the most meaningful of components.  In local and regional contexts
   and with improving technology, users might benefit from being able to
   use a wider range of characters; such use is not defined in this
   document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Syntax Notation and Common Elements">
<t>
   This document uses two conventions to describe and define the syntax
   for URI.  The first, called the layout form, is a general description
   of the order of components and component separators, as in
</t>
<figure><artwork>
    &lt;first&gt;/&lt;second&gt;;&lt;third&gt;?&lt;fourth&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The component names are enclosed in angle-brackets and any characters
   outside angle-brackets are literal separators.  Whitespace should be
   ignored.  These descriptions are used informally and do not define
   the syntax requirements.
</t>
<t>
   The second convention is a BNF-like grammar, used to define the
   formal URI syntax.  The grammar is that of <xref target="RFC822"/>, except that "|"
   is used to designate alternatives.  Briefly, rules are separated from
   definitions by an equal "=", indentation is used to continue a rule
   definition over more than one line, literals are quoted with "",
   parentheses "(" and ")" are used to group elements, optional elements
   are enclosed in "[" and "]" brackets, and elements may be preceded
   with &lt;n&gt;* to designate n or more repetitions of the following
   element; n defaults to 0.
</t>
<t>
   Unlike many specifications that use a BNF-like grammar to define the
   bytes (octets) allowed by a protocol, the URI grammar is defined in
   terms of characters.  Each literal in the grammar corresponds to the
   character it represents, rather than to the octet encoding of that
   character in any particular coded character set.  How a URI is
   represented in terms of bits and bytes on the wire is dependent upon
   the character encoding of the protocol used to transport it, or the
   charset of the document which contains it.
</t>
<figure><preamble>
   The following definitions are common to many elements:
</preamble>
<iref item="alpha" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="alpha" primary="true"/>
<iref item="lowalpha" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="lowalpha" primary="true"/>
<iref item="upalpha" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="upalpha" primary="true"/>
<iref item="digit" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="digit" primary="true"/>
<iref item="alphanum" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="alphanum" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
    alpha    = lowalpha | upalpha

    lowalpha = "a" | "b" | "c" | "d" | "e" | "f" | "g" | "h" | "i" |
               "j" | "k" | "l" | "m" | "n" | "o" | "p" | "q" | "r" |
               "s" | "t" | "u" | "v" | "w" | "x" | "y" | "z"

    upalpha  = "A" | "B" | "C" | "D" | "E" | "F" | "G" | "H" | "I" |
               "J" | "K" | "L" | "M" | "N" | "O" | "P" | "Q" | "R" |
               "S" | "T" | "U" | "V" | "W" | "X" | "Y" | "Z"

    digit    = "0" | "1" | "2" | "3" | "4" | "5" | "6" | "7" |
               "8" | "9"

    alphanum = alpha | digit
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The complete URI syntax is collected in Appendix A.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="URI Characters and Escape Sequences">
<t>
   URI consist of a restricted set of characters, primarily chosen to
   aid transcribability and usability both in computer systems and in
   non-computer communications. Characters used conventionally as
   delimiters around URI were excluded.  The restricted set of
   characters consists of digits, letters, and a few graphic symbols
   were chosen from those common to most of the character encodings and
   input facilities available to Internet users.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="uric" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="uric" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
uric          = reserved | unreserved | escaped
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Within a URI, characters are either used as delimiters, or to
   represent strings of data (octets) within the delimited portions.
   Octets are either represented directly by a character (using the US-ASCII
   character for that octet <xref target="ASCII"/>) or by an escape encoding.
   This representation is elaborated below.
</t>

<section title="URI and non-ASCII characters">
<t>
   The relationship between URI and characters has been a source of
   confusion for characters that are not part of US-ASCII. To describe
   the relationship, it is useful to distinguish between a "character"
   (as a distinguishable semantic entity) and an "octet" (an 8-bit
   byte). There are two mappings, one from URI characters to octets, and
   a second from octets to original characters:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
URI character sequence->octet sequence->original character sequence
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   A URI is represented as a sequence of characters, not as a sequence
   of octets. That is because URI might be "transported" by means that
   are not through a computer network, e.g., printed on paper, read over
   the radio, etc.
</t>
<t>
   A URI scheme may define a mapping from URI characters to octets;
   whether this is done depends on the scheme. Commonly, within a
   delimited component of a URI, a sequence of characters may be used to
   represent a sequence of octets. For example, the character "a"
   represents the octet 97 (decimal), while the character sequence "%",
   "0", "a" represents the octet 10 (decimal).
</t>
<t>
   There is a second translation for some resources: the sequence of
   octets defined by a component of the URI is subsequently used to
   represent a sequence of characters. A 'charset' defines this mapping.
   There are many charsets in use in Internet protocols. For example,
   UTF-8 <xref target="UTF-8"/> defines a mapping from sequences of octets to sequences
   of characters in the repertoire of ISO 10646.
</t>
<t>
   In the simplest case, the original character sequence contains only
   characters that are defined in US-ASCII, and the two levels of
   mapping are simple and easily invertible: each 'original character'
   is represented as the octet for the US-ASCII code for it, which is,
   in turn, represented as either the US-ASCII character, or else the
   "%" escape sequence for that octet.
</t>
<t>
   For original character sequences that contain non-ASCII characters,
   however, the situation is more difficult. Internet protocols that
   transmit octet sequences intended to represent character sequences
   are expected to provide some way of identifying the charset used, if
   there might be more than one <xref target="RFC2277"/>.  However, there is currently
   no provision within the generic URI syntax to accomplish this
   identification. An individual URI scheme may require a single
   charset, define a default charset, or provide a way to indicate the
   charset used.
</t>
<t>
   It is expected that a systematic treatment of character encoding
   within URI will be developed as a future modification of this
   specification.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Reserved Characters">
<t>
   Many URI include components consisting of or delimited by, certain
   special characters.  These characters are called "reserved", since
   their usage within the URI component is limited to their reserved
   purpose.  If the data for a URI component would conflict with the
   reserved purpose, then the conflicting data must be escaped before
   forming the URI.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="reserved" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="reserved" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
reserved    = ";" | "/" | "?" | ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" |
              "$" | ","
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The "reserved" syntax class above refers to those characters that are
   allowed within a URI, but which may not be allowed within a
   particular component of the generic URI syntax; they are used as
   delimiters of the components described in Section 3.
</t>
<t>
   Characters in the "reserved" set are not reserved in all contexts.
   The set of characters actually reserved within any given URI
   component is defined by that component. In general, a character is
   reserved if the semantics of the URI changes if the character is
   replaced with its escaped US-ASCII encoding.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Unreserved Characters">
<t>
   Data characters that are allowed in a URI but do not have a reserved
   purpose are called unreserved.  These include upper and lower case
   letters, decimal digits, and a limited set of punctuation marks and
   symbols.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="unreserved" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="unreserved" primary="true"/>
<iref item="mark" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="mark" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
unreserved  = alphanum | mark

mark        = "-" | "_" | "." | "!" | "~" | "*" | "'" | "(" | ")"
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Unreserved characters can be escaped without changing the semantics
   of the URI, but this should not be done unless the URI is being used
   in a context that does not allow the unescaped character to appear.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Escape Sequences">
<t>
   Data must be escaped if it does not have a representation using an
   unreserved character; this includes data that does not correspond to
   a printable character of the US-ASCII coded character set, or that
   corresponds to any US-ASCII character that is disallowed, as
   explained below.
</t>

<section title="Escaped Encoding">
<t>
   An escaped octet is encoded as a character triplet, consisting of the
   percent character "%" followed by the two hexadecimal digits
   representing the octet code. For example, "%20" is the escaped
   encoding for the US-ASCII space character.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="escaped" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="escaped" primary="true"/>
<iref item="hex" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="hex" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
escaped     = "%" hex hex
hex         = digit | "A" | "B" | "C" | "D" | "E" | "F" |
                      "a" | "b" | "c" | "d" | "e" | "f"
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="When to Escape and Unescape">
<t>
   A URI is always in an "escaped" form, since escaping or unescaping a
   completed URI might change its semantics.  Normally, the only time
   escape encodings can safely be made is when the URI is being created
   from its component parts; each component may have its own set of
   characters that are reserved, so only the mechanism responsible for
   generating or interpreting that component can determine whether or
   not escaping a character will change its semantics. Likewise, a URI
   must be separated into its components before the escaped characters
   within those components can be safely decoded.
</t>
<t>
   In some cases, data that could be represented by an unreserved
   character may appear escaped; for example, some of the unreserved
   "mark" characters are automatically escaped by some systems.  If the
   given URI scheme defines a canonicalization algorithm, then
   unreserved characters may be unescaped according to that algorithm.
   For example, "%7e" is sometimes used instead of "~" in an http URL
   path, but the two are equivalent for an http URL.
</t>
<t>
   Because the percent "%" character always has the reserved purpose of
   being the escape indicator, it must be escaped as "%25" in order to
   be used as data within a URI.  Implementers should be careful not to
   escape or unescape the same string more than once, since unescaping
   an already unescaped string might lead to misinterpreting a percent
   data character as another escaped character, or vice versa in the
   case of escaping an already escaped string.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Excluded US-ASCII Characters">
<t>
   Although they are disallowed within the URI syntax, we include here a
   description of those US-ASCII characters that have been excluded and
   the reasons for their exclusion.
</t>
<t>
   The control characters in the US-ASCII coded character set are not
   used within a URI, both because they are non-printable and because
   they are likely to be misinterpreted by some control mechanisms.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="control" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="control" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
control     = &lt;US-ASCII coded characters 00-1F and 7F hexadecimal&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The space character is excluded because significant spaces may
   disappear and insignificant spaces may be introduced when URI are
   transcribed or typeset or subjected to the treatment of word-processing
   programs.  Whitespace is also used to delimit URI in many
   contexts.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="space" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="space" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
space       = &lt;US-ASCII coded character 20 hexadecimal&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The angle-bracket "&lt;" and "&gt;" and double-quote (") characters are
   excluded because they are often used as the delimiters around URI in
   text documents and protocol fields.  The character "#" is excluded
   because it is used to delimit a URI from a fragment identifier in URI
   references (Section 4). The percent character "%" is excluded because
   it is used for the encoding of escaped characters.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="delims" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="delims" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
delims      = "&lt;" | "&gt;" | "#" | "%" | &lt;"&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Other characters are excluded because gateways and other transport
   agents are known to sometimes modify such characters, or they are
   used as delimiters.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="unwise" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="unwise" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
unwise      = "{" | "}" | "|" | "\" | "^" | "[" | "]" | "`"
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Data corresponding to excluded characters must be escaped in order to
   be properly represented within a URI.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section title="URI Syntactic Components">
<t>
   The URI syntax is dependent upon the scheme.  In general, absolute
   URI are written as follows:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;scheme&gt;:&lt;scheme-specific-part&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   An absolute URI contains the name of the scheme being used (&lt;scheme&gt;)
   followed by a colon (":") and then a string (the &lt;scheme-specific-part&gt;)
   whose interpretation depends on the scheme.
</t>
<t>
   The URI syntax does not require that the scheme-specific-part have
   any general structure or set of semantics which is common among all
   URI.  However, a subset of URI do share a common syntax for
   representing hierarchical relationships within the namespace.  This
   "generic URI" syntax consists of a sequence of four main components:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;scheme&gt;://&lt;authority&gt;&lt;path&gt;?&lt;query&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   each of which, except &lt;scheme&gt;, may be absent from a particular URI.
   For example, some URI schemes do not allow an &lt;authority&gt; component,
   and others do not use a &lt;query&gt; component.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="absoluteURI" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="absoluteURI" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
absoluteURI   = scheme ":" ( hier_part | opaque_part )
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   URI that are hierarchical in nature use the slash "/" character for
   separating hierarchical components.  For some file systems, a "/"
   character (used to denote the hierarchical structure of a URI) is the
   delimiter used to construct a file name hierarchy, and thus the URI
   path will look similar to a file pathname.  This does NOT imply that
   the resource is a file or that the URI maps to an actual filesystem
   pathname.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="hier_part" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="hier_part" primary="true"/>
<iref item="net_path" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="net_path" primary="true"/>
<iref item="abs_path" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="abs_path" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
hier_part     = [ net_path | abs_path ] [ "?" query ]

net_path      = "//" authority [ abs_path ]

abs_path      = "/"  path_segments
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   URI that do not make use of the slash "/" character for separating
   hierarchical components are considered opaque by the generic URI
   parser.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="opaque_part" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="opaque_part" primary="true"/>
<iref item="uric_no_slash" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="uric_no_slash" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
opaque_part   = uric_no_slash *uric

uric_no_slash = unreserved | escaped | ";" | "?" | ":" | "@" |
                "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | ","
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   We use the term &lt;path&gt; to refer to both the &lt;abs_path&gt; and
   &lt;opaque_part&gt; constructs, since they are mutually exclusive for any
   given URI and can be parsed as a single component.
</t>

<section title="Scheme Component">
<t>
   Just as there are many different methods of access to resources,
   there are a variety of schemes for identifying such resources.  The
   URI syntax consists of a sequence of components separated by reserved
   characters, with the first component defining the semantics for the
   remainder of the URI string.
</t>
<t>
   Scheme names consist of a sequence of characters beginning with a
   lower case letter and followed by any combination of lower case
   letters, digits, plus ("+"), period ("."), or hyphen ("-").  For
   resiliency, programs interpreting URI should treat upper case letters
   as equivalent to lower case in scheme names (e.g., allow "HTTP" as
   well as "http").
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="scheme" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="scheme" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
scheme        = alpha *( alpha | digit | "+" | "-" | "." )
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Relative URI references are distinguished from absolute URI in that
   they do not begin with a scheme name.  Instead, the scheme is
   inherited from the base URI, as described in Section 5.2.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Authority Component">
<t>
   Many URI schemes include a top hierarchical element for a naming
   authority, such that the namespace defined by the remainder of the
   URI is governed by that authority.  This authority component is
   typically defined by an Internet-based server or a scheme-specific
   registry of naming authorities.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="authority" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="authority" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
authority     = server | reg_name
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The authority component is preceded by a double slash "//" and is
   terminated by the next slash "/", question-mark "?", or by the end of
   the URI.  Within the authority component, the characters ";", ":",
   "@", "?", and "/" are reserved.
</t>
<t>
   An authority component is not required for a URI scheme to make use
   of relative references.  A base URI without an authority component
   implies that any relative reference will also be without an authority
   component.
</t>

<section title="Registry-based Naming Authority">
<t>
   The structure of a registry-based naming authority is specific to the
   URI scheme, but constrained to the allowed characters for an
   authority component.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="reg_name" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="reg_name" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
reg_name      = 1*( unreserved | escaped | "$" | "," |
                    ";" | ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" )
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Server-based Naming Authority">
<t>
   URL schemes that involve the direct use of an IP-based protocol to a
   specified server on the Internet use a common syntax for the server
   component of the URI's scheme-specific data:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;userinfo&gt;@&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   where &lt;userinfo&gt; may consist of a user name and, optionally,
   scheme-specific information about how to gain authorization to access the
   server.  The parts "&lt;userinfo&gt;@" and ":&lt;port&gt;" may be omitted.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="server" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="server" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
server        = [ [ userinfo "@" ] hostport ]
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The user information, if present, is followed by a commercial at-sign
   "@".
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="userinfo" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="userinfo" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
userinfo      = *( unreserved | escaped |
                   ";" | ":" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | "," )
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Some URL schemes use the format "user:password" in the userinfo
   field. This practice is NOT RECOMMENDED, because the passing of
   authentication information in clear text (such as URI) has proven to
   be a security risk in almost every case where it has been used.
</t>
<t>
   The host is a domain name of a network host, or its IPv4 address as a
   set of four decimal digit groups separated by ".".  Literal IPv6
   addresses are not supported.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="hostport" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="hostport" primary="true"/>
<iref item="host" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="host" primary="true"/>
<iref item="hostname" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="hostname" primary="true"/>
<iref item="domainlabel" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="domainlabel" primary="true"/>
<iref item="toplabel" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="toplabel" primary="true"/>
<iref item="IPv4address" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="IPv4address" primary="true"/>
<iref item="port" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="port" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
hostport      = host [ ":" port ]
host          = hostname | IPv4address
hostname      = *( domainlabel "." ) toplabel [ "." ]
domainlabel   = alphanum | alphanum *( alphanum | "-" ) alphanum
toplabel      = alpha | alpha *( alphanum | "-" ) alphanum
IPv4address   = 1*digit "." 1*digit "." 1*digit "." 1*digit
port          = *digit
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Hostnames take the form described in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC1034"/> and
   Section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC1123"/>: a sequence of domain labels separated by
   ".", each domain label starting and ending with an alphanumeric
   character and possibly also containing "-" characters.  The rightmost
   domain label of a fully qualified domain name will never start with a
   digit, thus syntactically distinguishing domain names from IPv4
   addresses, and may be followed by a single "." if it is necessary to
   distinguish between the complete domain name and any local domain.
   To actually be "Uniform" as a resource locator, a URL hostname should
   be a fully qualified domain name.  In practice, however, the host
   component may be a local domain literal.
</t>
<t>
  <list><t>
      Note: A suitable representation for including a literal IPv6
      address as the host part of a URL is desired, but has not yet been
      determined or implemented in practice.
  </t></list>
</t>
<t>
   The port is the network port number for the server.  Most schemes
   designate protocols that have a default port number.  Another port
   number may optionally be supplied, in decimal, separated from the
   host by a colon.  If the port is omitted, the default port number is
   assumed.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Path Component">
<t>
   The path component contains data, specific to the authority (or the
   scheme if there is no authority component), identifying the resource
   within the scope of that scheme and authority.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="path" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="path" primary="true"/>
<iref item="path_segments" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="path_segments" primary="true"/>
<iref item="segment" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="segment" primary="true"/>
<iref item="param" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="param" primary="true"/>
<iref item="pchar" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="pchar" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
path          = [ abs_path | opaque_part ]

path_segments = segment *( "/" segment )
segment       = *pchar *( ";" param )
param         = *pchar

pchar         = unreserved | escaped |
                ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | ","
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The path may consist of a sequence of path segments separated by a
   single slash "/" character.  Within a path segment, the characters
   "/", ";", "=", and "?" are reserved.  Each path segment may include a
   sequence of parameters, indicated by the semicolon ";" character.
   The parameters are not significant to the parsing of relative
   references.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Query Component">
<t>
   The query component is a string of information to be interpreted by
   the resource.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="query" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="query" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
query         = *uric
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Within a query component, the characters ";", "/", "?", ":", "@",
   "&amp;", "=", "+", ",", and "$" are reserved.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="URI References">
<t>
   The term "URI-reference" is used here to denote the common usage of a
   resource identifier.  A URI reference may be absolute or relative,
   and may have additional information attached in the form of a
   fragment identifier.  However, "the URI" that results from such a
   reference includes only the absolute URI after the fragment
   identifier (if any) is removed and after any relative URI is resolved
   to its absolute form.  Although it is possible to limit the
   discussion of URI syntax and semantics to that of the absolute
   result, most usage of URI is within general URI references, and it is
   impossible to obtain the URI from such a reference without also
   parsing the fragment and resolving the relative form.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="URI-reference" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="URI-reference" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
URI-reference = [ absoluteURI | relativeURI ] [ "#" fragment ]
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The syntax for relative URI is a shortened form of that for absolute
   URI, where some prefix of the URI is missing and certain path
   components ("." and "..") have a special meaning when, and only when,
   interpreting a relative path.  The relative URI syntax is defined in
   Section 5.
</t>

<section title="Fragment Identifier">
<t>
   When a URI reference is used to perform a retrieval action on the
   identified resource, the optional fragment identifier, separated from
   the URI by a crosshatch ("#") character, consists of additional
   reference information to be interpreted by the user agent after the
   retrieval action has been successfully completed.  As such, it is not
   part of a URI, but is often used in conjunction with a URI.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="fragment" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="fragment" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
fragment      = *uric
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The semantics of a fragment identifier is a property of the data
   resulting from a retrieval action, regardless of the type of URI used
   in the reference.  Therefore, the format and interpretation of
   fragment identifiers is dependent on the media type <xref target="RFC2046"/> of the
   retrieval result.  The character restrictions described in Section 2
   for URI also apply to the fragment in a URI-reference.  Individual
   media types may define additional restrictions or structure within
   the fragment for specifying different types of "partial views" that
   can be identified within that media type.
</t>
<t>
   A fragment identifier is only meaningful when a URI reference is
   intended for retrieval and the result of that retrieval is a document
   for which the identified fragment is consistently defined.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Same-document References">
<t>
   A URI reference that does not contain a URI is a reference to the
   current document.  In other words, an empty URI reference within a
   document is interpreted as a reference to the start of that document,
   and a reference containing only a fragment identifier is a reference
   to the identified fragment of that document.  Traversal of such a
   reference should not result in an additional retrieval action.
   However, if the URI reference occurs in a context that is always
   intended to result in a new request, as in the case of HTML's FORM
   element, then an empty URI reference represents the base URI of the
   current document and should be replaced by that URI when transformed
   into a request.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Parsing a URI Reference">
<t>
   A URI reference is typically parsed according to the four main
   components and fragment identifier in order to determine what
   components are present and whether the reference is relative or
   absolute.  The individual components are then parsed for their
   subparts and, if not opaque, to verify their validity.
</t>
<t>
   Although the BNF defines what is allowed in each component, it is
   ambiguous in terms of differentiating between an authority component
   and a path component that begins with two slash characters.  The
   greedy algorithm is used for disambiguation: the left-most matching
   rule soaks up as much of the URI reference string as it is capable of
   matching.  In other words, the authority component wins.
</t>
<t>
   Readers familiar with regular expressions should see Appendix B for a
   concrete parsing example and test oracle.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Relative URI References">
<t>
   It is often the case that a group or "tree" of documents has been
   constructed to serve a common purpose; the vast majority of URI in
   these documents point to resources within the tree rather than
   outside of it.  Similarly, documents located at a particular site are
   much more likely to refer to other resources at that site than to
   resources at remote sites.
</t>
<t>
   Relative addressing of URI allows document trees to be partially
   independent of their location and access scheme.  For instance, it is
   possible for a single set of hypertext documents to be simultaneously
   accessible and traversable via each of the "file", "http", and "ftp"
   schemes if the documents refer to each other using relative URI.
   Furthermore, such document trees can be moved, as a whole, without
   changing any of the relative references.  Experience within the WWW
   has demonstrated that the ability to perform relative referencing is
   necessary for the long-term usability of embedded URI.
</t>
<t>
   The syntax for relative URI takes advantage of the &lt;hier_part&gt; syntax
   of &lt;absoluteURI&gt; (Section 3) in order to express a reference that is
   relative to the namespace of another hierarchical URI.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="relativeURI" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="relativeURI" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
relativeURI   = [ net_path | abs_path | rel_path ] [ "?" query ]
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   A relative reference beginning with two slash characters is termed a
   network-path reference, as defined by &lt;net_path&gt; in Section 3.  Such
   references are rarely used.
</t>
<t>
   A relative reference beginning with a single slash character is
   termed an absolute-path reference, as defined by &lt;abs_path&gt; in
   Section 3.
</t>
<t>
   A relative reference that does not begin with a scheme name or a
   slash character is termed a relative-path reference.
</t>
<figure>
<iref item="rel_path" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="rel_path" primary="true"/>
<iref item="rel_segment" primary="true"/><iref item="URI grammar" subitem="rel_segment" primary="true"/>
<artwork>
rel_path      = rel_segment [ abs_path ]

rel_segment   = 1*( unreserved | escaped |
                    ";" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | "," )
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Within a relative-path reference, the complete path segments "." and
   ".." have special meanings: "the current hierarchy level" and "the
   level above this hierarchy level", respectively.  Although this is
   very similar to their use within Unix-based filesystems to indicate
   directory levels, these path components are only considered special
   when resolving a relative-path reference to its absolute form
   (Section 5.2).
</t>
<t>
   Authors should be aware that a path segment which contains a colon
   character cannot be used as the first segment of a relative URI path
   (e.g., "this:that"), because it would be mistaken for a scheme name.
   It is therefore necessary to precede such segments with other
   segments (e.g., "./this:that") in order for them to be referenced as
   a relative path.
</t>
<t>
   It is not necessary for all URI within a given scheme to be
   restricted to the &lt;hier_part&gt; syntax, since the hierarchical
   properties of that syntax are only necessary when relative URI are
   used within a particular document.  Documents can only make use of
   relative URI when their base URI fits within the &lt;hier_part&gt; syntax.
   It is assumed that any document which contains a relative reference
   will also have a base URI that obeys the syntax.  In other words,
   relative URI cannot be used within a document that has an unsuitable
   base URI.
</t>
<t>
   Some URI schemes do not allow a hierarchical syntax matching the
   &lt;hier_part&gt; syntax, and thus cannot use relative references.
</t>

<section title="Establishing a Base URI">
<t>
   The term "relative URI" implies that there exists some absolute "base
   URI" against which the relative reference is applied.  Indeed, the
   base URI is necessary to define the semantics of any relative URI
   reference; without it, a relative reference is meaningless.  In order
   for relative URI to be usable within a document, the base URI of that
   document must be known to the parser.
</t>
<t>
   The base URI of a document can be established in one of four ways,
   listed below in order of precedence.  The order of precedence can be
   thought of in terms of layers, where the innermost defined base URI
   has the highest precedence.  This can be visualized graphically as:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
.----------------------------------------------------------.
|  .----------------------------------------------------.  |
|  |  .----------------------------------------------.  |  |
|  |  |  .----------------------------------------.  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  .----------------------------------.  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  |       &lt;relative_reference&gt;       |  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |  `----------------------------------'  |  |  |  |
|  |  |  | (5.1.1) Base URI embedded in the       |  |  |  |
|  |  |  |         document's content             |  |  |  |
|  |  |  `----------------------------------------'  |  |  |
|  |  | (5.1.2) Base URI of the encapsulating entity |  |  |
|  |  |         (message, document, or none).        |  |  |
|  |  `----------------------------------------------'  |  |
|  | (5.1.3) URI used to retrieve the entity            |  |
|  `----------------------------------------------------'  |
| (5.1.4) Default Base URI is application-dependent        |
`----------------------------------------------------------'
</artwork></figure>

<section title="Base URI within Document Content">
<t>
   Within certain document media types, the base URI of the document can
   be embedded within the content itself such that it can be readily
   obtained by a parser.  This can be useful for descriptive documents,
   such as tables of content, which may be transmitted to others through
   protocols other than their usual retrieval context (e.g., E-Mail or
   USENET news).
</t>
<t>
   It is beyond the scope of this document to specify how, for each
   media type, the base URI can be embedded.  It is assumed that user
   agents manipulating such media types will be able to obtain the
   appropriate syntax from that media type's specification.  An example
   of how the base URI can be embedded in the Hypertext Markup Language
   (HTML) <xref target="RFC1866"/> is provided in Appendix D.
</t>
<t>
   A mechanism for embedding the base URI within MIME container types
   (e.g., the message and multipart types) is defined by MHTML
   <xref target="RFC2110"/>.  Protocols that do not use the MIME message header syntax,
   but which do allow some form of tagged metainformation to be included
   within messages, may define their own syntax for defining the base
   URI as part of a message.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Base URI from the Encapsulating Entity">
<t>
   If no base URI is embedded, the base URI of a document is defined by
   the document's retrieval context.  For a document that is enclosed
   within another entity (such as a message or another document), the
   retrieval context is that entity; thus, the default base URI of the
   document is the base URI of the entity in which the document is
   encapsulated.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Base URI from the Retrieval URI">
<t>
   If no base URI is embedded and the document is not encapsulated
   within some other entity (e.g., the top level of a composite entity),
   then, if a URI was used to retrieve the base document, that URI shall
   be considered the base URI.  Note that if the retrieval was the
   result of a redirected request, the last URI used (i.e., that which
   resulted in the actual retrieval of the document) is the base URI.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Default Base URI">
<t>
   If none of the conditions described in Sections 5.1.1--5.1.3 apply,
   then the base URI is defined by the context of the application.
   Since this definition is necessarily application-dependent, failing
   to define the base URI using one of the other methods may result in
   the same content being interpreted differently by different types of
   application.
</t>
<t>
   It is the responsibility of the distributor(s) of a document
   containing relative URI to ensure that the base URI for that document
   can be established.  It must be emphasized that relative URI cannot
   be used reliably in situations where the document's base URI is not
   well-defined.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Resolving Relative References to Absolute Form">
<t>
   This section describes an example algorithm for resolving URI
   references that might be relative to a given base URI.  The algorithm
   is intended to provide a definitive result that can be used to test
   the output of other implementations.  Implementation of the algorithm
   itself is not required, but the result given by an implementation must
   match the result that would be given by this algorithm.
</t>
<t>
   The base URI is established according to the rules of Section 5.1 and
   parsed into the four main components as described in Section 3.  Note
   that only the scheme component is required to be present in the base
   URI; the other components may be empty or undefined.  A component is
   undefined if its preceding separator does not appear in the URI
   reference; the path component is never undefined, though it may be
   empty.  The base URI's query component is not used by the resolution
   algorithm and may be discarded.
</t>
<figure><preamble>
   For each URI reference (R), the following pseudocode describes an
   algorithm for transforming R into its target (T), which is either
   an absolute URI or the current document, and R's optional fragment:
</preamble>
<artwork>
(R.scheme, R.authority, R.path, R.query, fragment) = parse(R);
   -- The URI reference is parsed into the four components and
   -- fragment identifier, as described in Section 4.3.

if ((not validating) and (R.scheme == Base.scheme)) then
   -- For compatibility, a non-validating parser may ignore a scheme
   -- in the reference if it is identical to the base URI's scheme.
   undefine(R.scheme);
endif;

if defined(R.scheme) then
   T.scheme    = R.scheme;
   T.authority = R.authority;
   T.path      = R.path;
   T.query     = R.query;
else
   if defined(R.authority) then
      T.authority = R.authority;
      T.path      = R.path;
      T.query     = R.query;
   else
      if (R.path == "") then
         if defined(R.query) then
            T.path  = Base.path;
            T.query = R.query;
         else
            -- An empty reference refers to the current document
            return (current_document, fragment);
         endif;
      else
         if (R.path starts-with "/") then
            T.path = R.path;
         else
            T.path = merge(Base.path, R.path);
         endif;
         T.query = R.query;
      endif;
      T.authority = Base.authority;
   endif;
   T.scheme = Base.scheme;
endif;

return (T, fragment);
</artwork></figure>
<t>
The pseudocode above refers to a merge routine for merging a
relative-path reference with the path of the base URI to obtain the
target path.  Although there are many ways to do this, we will describe
a simple method using a separate string buffer:
  <list style="numbers">
  <t>
All but the last segment of the base URI's path component is
copied to the buffer.  In other words, any characters after the
last (right-most) slash character, if any, are excluded.
If the base URI's path component is the empty string, then
a single slash character ("/") is copied to the buffer.
  </t>
  <t>
The reference's path component is appended to the buffer
string.
  </t>
  <t>
All occurrences of "./", where "." is a complete path segment,
are removed from the buffer string.
  </t>
  <t>
If the buffer string ends with "." as a complete path segment,
that "." is removed.
  </t>
  <t>
All occurrences of "&lt;segment&gt;/../", where &lt;segment&gt; is a
complete path segment not equal to "..", are removed from the
buffer string.  Removal of these path segments is performed
iteratively, removing the leftmost matching pattern on each
iteration, until no matching pattern remains.
  </t>
  <t>
If the buffer string ends with "&lt;segment&gt;/..", where &lt;segment&gt;
is a complete path segment not equal to "..", that
"&lt;segment&gt;/.." is removed.
  </t>
  <t>
If the resulting buffer string still begins with one or more
complete path segments of "..", then the reference is
considered to be in error.  Implementations may handle this
error by retaining these components in the resolved path (i.e.,
treating them as part of the final URI), by removing them from
the resolved path (i.e., discarding relative levels above the
root), or by avoiding traversal of the reference.
  </t>
  <t>
The remaining buffer string is the target URI's path component.
  </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
   Some systems may find it more efficient to implement the merge
   algorithm as a pair of path segment stacks being merged, rather
   than as a series of string pattern replacements.
  <list>
    <t>
      Note: Some WWW client applications will fail to separate the
      reference's query component from its path component before merging
      the base and reference paths.  This may result in a loss of
      information if the query component contains the strings "/../" or "/./".
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<figure><preamble>
The resulting target URI components and fragment can be
recombined to provide the absolute form of the URI reference.
Using pseudocode, this would be:
</preamble><artwork>
result = ""

if defined(T.scheme) then
   append T.scheme to result;
   append ":" to result;
endif;

if defined(T.authority) then
   append "//" to result;
   append T.authority to result;
endif;

append T.path to result;

if defined(T.query) then
   append "?" to result;
   append T.query to result;
endif;

if defined(fragment) then
   append "#" to result;
   append fragment to result;
endif;

return result;
</artwork><postamble>
Note that we must be careful to preserve the distinction between a
component that is undefined, meaning that its separator was not
present in the reference, and a component that is empty, meaning
that the separator was present and was immediately followed by the
next component separator or the end of the reference.
</postamble></figure>
<t>
   Resolution examples are provided in Appendix C.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="URI Normalization and Equivalence">
<t>
   In many cases, different URI strings may actually identify the
   identical resource. For example, the host names used in URL are
   actually case insensitive, and the URL &lt;http://www.XEROX.com&gt; is
   equivalent to &lt;http://www.xerox.com&gt;. In general, the rules for
   equivalence and definition of a normal form, if any, are scheme
   dependent. When a scheme uses elements of the common syntax, it will
   also use the common syntax equivalence rules, namely that the scheme
   and hostname are case insensitive and a URL with an explicit ":port",
   where the port is the default for the scheme, is equivalent to one
   where the port is elided.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   A URI does not in itself pose a security threat.  Users should beware
   that there is no general guarantee that a URL, which at one time
   located a given resource, will continue to do so.  Nor is there any
   guarantee that a URL will not locate a different resource at some
   later point in time, due to the lack of any constraint on how a given
   authority apportions its namespace.  Such a guarantee can only be
   obtained from the person(s) controlling that namespace and the
   resource in question.  A specific URI scheme may include additional
   semantics, such as name persistence, if those semantics are required
   of all naming authorities for that scheme.
</t>
<t>
   It is sometimes possible to construct a URL such that an attempt to
   perform a seemingly harmless, idempotent operation, such as the
   retrieval of an entity associated with the resource, will in fact
   cause a possibly damaging remote operation to occur.  The unsafe URL
   is typically constructed by specifying a port number other than that
   reserved for the network protocol in question.  The client
   unwittingly contacts a site that is in fact running a different
   protocol.  The content of the URL contains instructions that, when
   interpreted according to this other protocol, cause an unexpected
   operation.  An example has been the use of a gopher URL to cause an
   unintended or impersonating message to be sent via a SMTP server.
</t>
<t>
   Caution should be used when using any URL that specifies a port
   number other than the default for the protocol, especially when it is
   a number within the reserved space.
</t>
<t>
   Care should be taken when a URL contains escaped delimiters for a
   given protocol (for example, CR and LF characters for telnet
   protocols) that these are not unescaped before transmission.  This
   might violate the protocol, but avoids the potential for such
   characters to be used to simulate an extra operation or parameter in
   that protocol, which might lead to an unexpected and possibly harmful
   remote operation to be performed.
</t>
<t>
   It is clearly unwise to use a URL that contains a password which is
   intended to be secret. In particular, the use of a password within
   the 'userinfo' component of a URL is strongly disrecommended except
   in those rare cases where the 'password' parameter is intended to be
   public.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
   This document is derived from RFC 2396 <xref target="RFC2396"/>,
   RFC 1738 <xref target="RFC1738"/> and RFC 1808 <xref target="RFC1808"/>;
   the acknowledgements in those specifications still apply.
   In addition, contributions by Reese Anschultz, Adam M. Costello,
   Bruce Lilly, Julian Reschke, Ronald Tschalaer, and Henry Zongaro
   are gratefully acknowledged.
</t>
</section>
</middle>
<back>
  <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="ASCII">
  <front>
    <title>Coded Character Set -- 7-bit American Standard Code for Information Interchange</title>
    <author>
      <organization>American National Standards Institute</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="" year="1986" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="ANSI" value="X3.4" />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1123'>
<front>
<title>Requirements for Internet Hosts - Application and Support</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Braden' fullname='Robert Braden'>
<organization>University of Southern California (USC), Information Sciences Institute</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
<city>Marina del Rey</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>90292-6695</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 213 822 1511</phone>
<email>Braden@ISI.EDU</email></address></author>
<date month='October' year='1989'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='3' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1123' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC822'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Standard for ARPA Internet Text Messages'>Standard for the format of ARPA Internet text messages</title>
<author initials='D.H.' surname='Crocker' fullname='David H. Crocker'>
<organization>University of Delaware, Dept. of Electrical Engineering</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Newark</city>
<region>DE</region>
<code>19711</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<email>DCrocker@UDel-Relay</email></address></author>
<date month='August' day='13' year='1982'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='11' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='822' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1034'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Domain Concepts and Facilities'>Domain names - concepts and facilities</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Mockapetris' fullname='P. Mockapetris'>
<organization>Information Sciences Institute (ISI)</organization></author>
<date month='November' year='1987'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='13' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1034' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='UTF-8'>
<front>
<title abbrev='UTF-8'>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
<author initials='F.' surname='Yergeau' fullname='Francois Yergeau'>
<organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>100, boul. Alexis-Nihon</street>
<street>Suite 600</street>
<city>Montreal</city>
<region>Quebec</region>
<code>H4M 2P2</code>
<country>CA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 514 747 2547</phone>
<facsimile>+1 514 747 2561</facsimile>
<email>fyergeau@alis.com</email></address></author>
<date month='January' year='1998'></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2279' />
</reference>
  
  </references>

  <references title="Non-normative References">
  
<reference anchor='RFC2277'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Charset Policy'>IETF Policy on Character Sets and Languages</title>
<author initials='H.T.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='Harald Tveit Alvestrand'>
<organization>UNINETT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>P.O.Box 6883 Elgeseter</street>
<street>N-7002 TRONDHEIM</street>
<country>NORWAY</country></postal>
<phone>+47 73 59 70 94</phone>
<email>Harald.T.Alvestrand@uninett.no</email></address></author>
<date month='January' year='1998'></date>
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>Internet Engineering Task Force</keyword>
<keyword>character encoding</keyword></front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='18' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2277' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1630'>
<front>
<title abbrev='URIs in WWW'>Universal Resource Identifiers in WWW: A Unifying Syntax for the Expression of Names and Addresses of Objects on the Network as used in the World-Wide Web</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization>CERN, World-Wide Web project</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1211 Geneva 23</street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>CH</country></postal>
<phone>+41 22 7673755</phone>
<facsimile>+41 22 7677155</facsimile>
<email>timbl@info.cern.ch</email></address></author>
<date month='June' year='1994'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1630' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1738'>
<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Locators (URL)</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization>CERN, World-Wide Web project</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1211 Geneva 23</street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>CH</country></postal>
<phone>+41 22 7673755</phone>
<facsimile>+41 22 7677155</facsimile>
<email>timbl@info.cern.ch</email></address></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
<organization>Xerox PARC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3333 Coyote Hill Road</street>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94034</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 812 4365</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 812 4333</facsimile>
<email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='McCahill' fullname='Mark McCahill'>
<organization>University of Minnesota, Computer and Information Services</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>100 Union Street SE, Shepherd Labs</street>
<street>Room 152</street>
<city>Minneapolis</city>
<region>MN</region>
<code>55455</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 612 625 1300</phone>
<email>mpm@boombox.micro.umn.edu</email></address></author>
<date month='December' year='1994'></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1738' />
</reference>
  
<reference anchor='RFC1866'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>545 Technology Square</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 253 9670</phone>
<facsimile>+1 617 258 8682</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email></address></author>
<author initials='D.W.' surname='Connolly' fullname='Daniel W. Connolly'>
<organization>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science, W3 Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>545 Technology Square</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 258 8682</phone>
<email>connolly@w3.org</email>
<uri>http://www.w3.org/hypertext/WWW/People/Connolly/</uri></address></author>
<date month='November' year='1995'></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1866' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC2396'>
<front>
<title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization abbrev='MIT/LCS'>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science, NE43-356</street>
<street>545 Technology Square</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code></postal>
<facsimile>+1(617)258-8682</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email></address></author>
<author initials='R.T.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
<organization abbrev='U.C. Irvine'>Department of Information and Computer Science</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>University of California, Irvine</street>
<city>Irvine</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92697-3425</code></postal>
<facsimile>+1(949)824-1715</facsimile>
<email>fielding@ics.uci.edu</email></address></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
<organization abbrev='Xerox Corporation'>Xerox PARC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3333 Coyote Hill Road</street>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94034</code></postal>
<facsimile>+1(415)812-4333</facsimile>
<email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email></address></author>
<date month='August' year='1998' />
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>resource</keyword>
<keyword>URI</keyword>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2396' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1808'>
<front>
<title>Relative Uniform Resource Locators</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
<organization>University of California Irvine, Department of Information and Computer Science</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Irvine</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92717-3425</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 714 824 4049</phone>
<facsimile>+1 714 824 4056</facsimile>
<email>fielding@ics.uci.edu</email></address></author>
<date month='June' year='1995'></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1808' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC2046'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Media Types'>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</title>
<author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='Ned Freed'>
<organization>Innosoft International, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
<city>West Covina</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>91790</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
<facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
<email>ned@innosoft.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='Nathaniel S. Borenstein'>
<organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
<city>Morristown</city>
<region>NJ</region>
<code>07960</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
<facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
<email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email></address></author>
<date month='November' year='1996'></date>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2046' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC2518">
<front>
<title>HTTP Extensions for Distributed Authoring -- WEBDAV</title>
<author initials="Y." surname="Goland" fullname="Y. Goland">
  <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
  <address><email>yarong@microsoft.com</email></address>
</author>
<author initials="E." surname="Whitehead" fullname="E. J. Whitehead, Jr.">
  <organization abbrev="UC Irvine">Dept. Of Information and Computer
Science, University of California, Irvine</organization>
  <address><email>ejw@ics.uci.edu</email></address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Faizi" fullname="A. Faizi">
  <organization abbrev="Netscape">Netscape</organization>
  <address><email>asad@netscape.com</email></address>
</author>
<author initials="S.R." surname="Carter" fullname="S. R. Carter">
  <organization abbrev="Novell">Novell</organization>
  <address><email>srcarter@novell.com</email></address>
</author>
<author initials="D." surname="Jensen" fullname="D. Jensen">
  <organization abbrev="Novell">Novell</organization>
  <address><email>dcjensen@novell.com</email></address>
</author>
<date month="February" year="1999"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2518"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1736'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Recommendations for IRLs'>Functional Recommendations for Internet Resource Locators</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Kunze' fullname='John A. Kunze'>
<organization>Information Systems and Technology</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>293 Evans Hall</street>
<city>Berkeley</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94720</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 510 642 1530</phone>
<facsimile>+1 510 643 5385</facsimile>
<email>jak@violet.berkeley.edu</email></address></author>
<date month='February' year='1995'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1736' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1737'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Requirements for Uniform Resource Names'>Functional Requirements for Uniform Resource Names</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
<organization>Xerox Palo Alto Research Center</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3333 Coyote Hill Road</street>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94304</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 812 4365</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 812 4333</facsimile>
<email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Sollins' fullname='Karen Sollins'>
<organization>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>545 Technology Square</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 253 2673</phone>
<email>sollins@lcs.mit.edu</email></address></author>
<date month='December' year='1994'></date></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1737' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC2141'>
<front>
<title>URN Syntax</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Moats' fullname='Ryan Moats'>
<organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>15621 Drexel Circle</street>
<street>Omaha</street>
<street>NE 68135-2358</street>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 402 894-9456</phone>
<email>jayhawk@ds.internic.net</email></address></author>
<date month='May' year='1997'></date>
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>URN</keyword>
<keyword>uniform resource</keyword>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2141' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='RFC2110'>
<front>
<title abbrev='MHTML'>MIME E-mail Encapsulation of Aggregate Documents, such as HTML (MHTML)</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Palme' fullname='Jacob Palme'>
<organization>Stockholm University and KTH</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Electrum 230</street>
<street>S-164 40 Kista</street>
<country>Sweden</country></postal>
<phone>+46-8-16 16 67</phone>
<facsimile>+46-8-783 08 29</facsimile>
<email>jpalme@dsv.su.se</email></address></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Hopmann' fullname='Alex Hopmann'>
<organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3590 North First Street</street>
<street>Suite 300</street>
<street>San Jose</street>
<street>CA 95134</street>
<street>Working group chairman:</street></postal>
<email>alexhop@microsoft.com</email></address></author>
<date month='March' year='1997'></date>
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>encapsulate</keyword>
<keyword>hypertext markup language</keyword>
<keyword>mail</keyword>
<keyword>multipurpose internet mail extensions</keyword>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2110' />
</reference>

</references>

<section title="Collected BNF for URI">
<figure><artwork>
URI-reference = [ absoluteURI | relativeURI ] [ "#" fragment ]
absoluteURI   = scheme ":" ( hier_part | opaque_part )
relativeURI   = [ net_path | abs_path | rel_path ] [ "?" query ]

hier_part     = [ net_path | abs_path ] [ "?" query ]
opaque_part   = uric_no_slash *uric

uric_no_slash = unreserved | escaped | ";" | "?" | ":" | "@" |
                "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | ","

net_path      = "//" authority [ abs_path ]
abs_path      = "/"  path_segments
rel_path      = rel_segment [ abs_path ]

rel_segment   = 1*( unreserved | escaped |
                    ";" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | "," )

scheme        = alpha *( alpha | digit | "+" | "-" | "." )

authority     = server | reg_name

reg_name      = 1*( unreserved | escaped | "$" | "," |
                    ";" | ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" )

server        = [ [ userinfo "@" ] hostport ]
userinfo      = *( unreserved | escaped |
                   ";" | ":" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | "," )

hostport      = host [ ":" port ]
host          = hostname | IPv4address
hostname      = *( domainlabel "." ) toplabel [ "." ]
domainlabel   = alphanum | alphanum *( alphanum | "-" ) alphanum
toplabel      = alpha | alpha *( alphanum | "-" ) alphanum
IPv4address   = 1*digit "." 1*digit "." 1*digit "." 1*digit
port          = *digit

path          = [ abs_path | opaque_part ]
path_segments = segment *( "/" segment )
segment       = *pchar *( ";" param )
param         = *pchar
pchar         = unreserved | escaped |
                ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" | "$" | ","

query         = *uric

fragment      = *uric

uric          = reserved | unreserved | escaped
reserved      = ";" | "/" | "?" | ":" | "@" | "&amp;" | "=" | "+" |
                "$" | ","
unreserved    = alphanum | mark
mark          = "-" | "_" | "." | "!" | "~" | "*" | "'" |
                "(" | ")"

escaped       = "%" hex hex
hex           = digit | "A" | "B" | "C" | "D" | "E" | "F" |
                        "a" | "b" | "c" | "d" | "e" | "f"

alphanum      = alpha | digit
alpha         = lowalpha | upalpha

lowalpha = "a" | "b" | "c" | "d" | "e" | "f" | "g" | "h" | "i" |
           "j" | "k" | "l" | "m" | "n" | "o" | "p" | "q" | "r" |
           "s" | "t" | "u" | "v" | "w" | "x" | "y" | "z"
upalpha  = "A" | "B" | "C" | "D" | "E" | "F" | "G" | "H" | "I" |
           "J" | "K" | "L" | "M" | "N" | "O" | "P" | "Q" | "R" |
           "S" | "T" | "U" | "V" | "W" | "X" | "Y" | "Z"
digit    = "0" | "1" | "2" | "3" | "4" | "5" | "6" | "7" |
           "8" | "9"
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Parsing a URI Reference with a Regular Expression">
<t>
   As described in Section 4.3, the generic URI syntax is not sufficient
   to disambiguate the components of some forms of URI.  Since the
   "greedy algorithm" described in that section is identical to the
   disambiguation method used by POSIX regular expressions, it is
   natural and commonplace to use a regular expression for parsing the
   potential four components and fragment identifier of a URI reference.
</t>
<t>
   The following line is the regular expression for breaking-down a URI
   reference into its components.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
^(([^:/?#]+):)?(//([^/?#]*))?([^?#]*)(\?([^#]*))?(#(.*))?
 12            3  4          5       6  7        8 9
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   The numbers in the second line above are only to assist readability;
   they indicate the reference points for each subexpression (i.e., each
   paired parenthesis).  We refer to the value matched for subexpression
   &lt;n&gt; as $&lt;n&gt;.  For example, matching the above expression to
</t>
<figure><artwork>
http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/uri/#Related
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   results in the following subexpression matches:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
$1 = http:
$2 = http
$3 = //www.ics.uci.edu
$4 = www.ics.uci.edu
$5 = /pub/ietf/uri/
$6 = &lt;undefined&gt;
$7 = &lt;undefined&gt;
$8 = #Related
$9 = Related
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   where &lt;undefined&gt; indicates that the component is not present, as is
   the case for the query component in the above example.  Therefore, we
   can determine the value of the four components and fragment as
</t>
<figure><artwork>
scheme    = $2
authority = $4
path      = $5
query     = $7
fragment  = $9
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   and, going in the opposite direction, we can recreate a URI reference
   from its components using the algorithm of Section 5.2.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Examples of Resolving Relative URI References">
<t>
   Within an object with a well-defined base URI of
</t>
<figure><artwork>
http://a/b/c/d;p?q
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   the relative URI would be resolved as follows:
</t>

<section title="Normal Examples">
<figure><artwork>
g:h           =  g:h
g             =  http://a/b/c/g
./g           =  http://a/b/c/g
g/            =  http://a/b/c/g/
/g            =  http://a/g
//g           =  http://g
?y            =  http://a/b/c/d;p?y
g?y           =  http://a/b/c/g?y
#s            =  (current document)#s
g#s           =  http://a/b/c/g#s
g?y#s         =  http://a/b/c/g?y#s
;x            =  http://a/b/c/;x
g;x           =  http://a/b/c/g;x
g;x?y#s       =  http://a/b/c/g;x?y#s
.             =  http://a/b/c/
./            =  http://a/b/c/
..            =  http://a/b/
../           =  http://a/b/
../g          =  http://a/b/g
../..         =  http://a/
../../        =  http://a/
../../g       =  http://a/g
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Abnormal Examples">
<t>
   Although the following abnormal examples are unlikely to occur in
   normal practice, all URI parsers should be capable of resolving them
   consistently.  Each example uses the same base as above.
</t>
<t>
   An empty reference refers to the start of the current document.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;&gt;            =  (current document)
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Parsers must be careful in handling the case where there are more
   relative path ".." segments than there are hierarchical levels in the
   base URI's path.  Note that the ".." syntax cannot be used to change
   the authority component of a URI.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
../../../g    =  http://a/../g
../../../../g =  http://a/../../g
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   In practice, some implementations strip leading relative symbolic
   elements (".", "..") after applying a relative URI calculation, based
   on the theory that compensating for obvious author errors is better
   than allowing the request to fail.  Thus, the above two references
   will be interpreted as "http://a/g" by some implementations.
</t>
<t>
   Similarly, parsers must avoid treating "." and ".." as special when
   they are not complete components of a relative path.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
/./g          =  http://a/./g
/../g         =  http://a/../g
g.            =  http://a/b/c/g.
.g            =  http://a/b/c/.g
g..           =  http://a/b/c/g..
..g           =  http://a/b/c/..g
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Less likely are cases where the relative URI uses unnecessary or
   nonsensical forms of the "." and ".." complete path segments.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
./../g        =  http://a/b/g
./g/.         =  http://a/b/c/g/
g/./h         =  http://a/b/c/g/h
g/../h        =  http://a/b/c/h
g;x=1/./y     =  http://a/b/c/g;x=1/y
g;x=1/../y    =  http://a/b/c/y
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Some applications fail to separate the reference's query and/or
   fragment components from a relative path before merging it with
   the base path.  This error is rarely noticed, since typical usage
   of a fragment never includes the hierarchy ("/") character, and the
   query component is not normally used within relative references.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
g?y/./x       =  http://a/b/c/g?y/./x
g?y/../x      =  http://a/b/c/g?y/../x
g#s/./x       =  http://a/b/c/g#s/./x
g#s/../x      =  http://a/b/c/g#s/../x
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Some parsers allow the scheme name to be present in a relative URI if
   it is the same as the base URI scheme.  This is considered to be a
   loophole in prior specifications of partial URI <xref target="RFC1630"/>.
   Its use should be avoided, but is allowed for backwards compatibility.
</t>
<figure><artwork>
http:g        =  http:g           ; for validating parsers
              |  http://a/b/c/g   ; for backwards compatibility
</artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Embedding the Base URI in HTML documents">
<t>
   It is useful to consider an example of how the base URI of a document
   can be embedded within the document's content.  In this appendix, we
   describe how documents written in the Hypertext Markup Language
   (HTML) <xref target="RFC1866"/> can include an embedded base URI.  This appendix
   does not form a part of the URI specification and should not be
   considered as anything more than a descriptive example.
</t>
<t>
   HTML defines a special element "BASE" which, when present in the
   "HEAD" portion of a document, signals that the parser should use the
   BASE element's "HREF" attribute as the base URI for resolving any
   relative URI.  The "HREF" attribute must be an absolute URI.  Note
   that, in HTML, element and attribute names are case-insensitive.  For
   example:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;!doctype html public "-//IETF//DTD HTML//EN"&gt;
&lt;HTML&gt;&lt;HEAD&gt;
&lt;TITLE&gt;An example HTML document&lt;/TITLE&gt;
&lt;BASE href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/Test/a/b/c"&gt;
&lt;/HEAD&gt;&lt;BODY&gt;
... &lt;A href="../x"&gt;a hypertext anchor&lt;/A&gt; ...
&lt;/BODY&gt;&lt;/HTML&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   A parser reading the example document should interpret the given
   relative URI "../x" as representing the absolute URI
</t>
<figure><artwork>
&lt;http://www.ics.uci.edu/Test/a/x&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   regardless of the context in which the example document was obtained.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Recommendations for Delimiting URI in Context">
<t>
   URI are often transmitted through formats that do not provide a clear
   context for their interpretation.  For example, there are many
   occasions when URI are included in plain text; examples include text
   sent in electronic mail, USENET news messages, and, most importantly,
   printed on paper.  In such cases, it is important to be able to
   delimit the URI from the rest of the text, and in particular from
   punctuation marks that might be mistaken for part of the URI.
</t>
<t>
   In practice, URI are delimited in a variety of ways, but usually
   within double-quotes "http://test.com/", angle brackets
   &lt;http://test.com/&gt;, or just using whitespace
</t>
<figure><artwork>
http://test.com/
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   These wrappers do not form part of the URI.
</t>
<t>
   In the case where a fragment identifier is associated with a URI
   reference, the fragment would be placed within the brackets as well
   (separated from the URI with a "#" character).
</t>
<t>
   In some cases, extra whitespace (spaces, linebreaks, tabs, etc.) may
   need to be added to break long URI across lines. The whitespace
   should be ignored when extracting the URI.
</t>
<t>
   No whitespace should be introduced after a hyphen ("-") character.
   Because some typesetters and printers may (erroneously) introduce a
   hyphen at the end of line when breaking a line, the interpreter of a
   URI containing a line break immediately after a hyphen should ignore
   all unescaped whitespace around the line break, and should be aware
   that the hyphen may or may not actually be part of the URI.
</t>
<t>
   Using &lt;&gt; angle brackets around each URI is especially recommended as
   a delimiting style for URI that contain whitespace.
</t>
<t>
   The prefix "URL:" (with or without a trailing space) was recommended
   as a way to used to help distinguish a URL from other bracketed
   designators, although this is not common in practice.
</t>
<t>
   For robustness, software that accepts user-typed URI should attempt
   to recognize and strip both delimiters and embedded whitespace.
</t>
<t>
   For example, the text:
  <list><t>
      Yes, Jim, I found it under "http://www.w3.org/Addressing/",
      but you can probably pick it up from &lt;ftp://ds.internic.
      net/rfc/&gt;.  Note the warning in &lt;http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/
      ietf/uri/historical.html#WARNING&gt;.
  </t></list>
</t>
<t>
   contains the URI references
</t>
<figure><artwork>
http://www.w3.org/Addressing/
ftp://ds.internic.net/rfc/
http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/uri/historical.html#WARNING
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Abbreviated URLs">
<t>
   The URL syntax was designed for unambiguous reference to network
   resources and extensibility via the URL scheme.  However, as URL
   identification and usage have become commonplace, traditional media
   (television, radio, newspapers, billboards, etc.) have increasingly
   used abbreviated URL references.  That is, a reference consisting of
   only the authority and path portions of the identified resource, such
   as
</t>
<figure><artwork>
www.w3.org/Addressing/
</artwork></figure>
<t>
   or simply the DNS hostname on its own.  Such references are primarily
   intended for human interpretation rather than machine, with the
   assumption that context-based heuristics are sufficient to complete
   the URL (e.g., most hostnames beginning with "www" are likely to have
   a URL prefix of "http://").  Although there is no standard set of
   heuristics for disambiguating abbreviated URL references, many client
   implementations allow them to be entered by the user and
   heuristically resolved.  It should be noted that such heuristics may
   change over time, particularly when new URL schemes are introduced.
</t>
<t>
   Since an abbreviated URL has the same syntax as a relative URL path,
   abbreviated URL references cannot be used in contexts where relative
   URLs are expected.  This limits the use of abbreviated URLs to places
   where there is no defined base URL, such as dialog boxes and off-line
   advertisements.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Summary of Non-editorial Changes">

<section title="Additions">
<t>
none yet
</t>
</section>

<section title="Modifications from RFC 2396">
<t>
The BNF of hier_part and relativeURI (Section 3) has been corrected
to allow a relative URI path to be empty.  This also allows an
absoluteURI to consist of nothing after the "scheme:", as is present
in practice with the "DAV:" namespace <xref target="RFC2518"/> and
the "about:" URI used by many browser implementations.
</t>
<t>
The resolving relative references algorithm of <xref target="RFC2396"/>
has been rewritten using pseudocode for this revision to improve clarity
and fix the following issues:
  <list style="symbols">
  <t>
    <xref target="RFC2396"/> section 5.2, step 6a, failed to account for
    a base URI with no path.
  </t>
  <t>
    Restored the behavior of <xref target="RFC1808"/> where, if the
    the reference contains an empty path and a defined query component,
    then the target URI inherits the base URI's path component.
  </t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
